<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A True narrative of the confession and execution of Ensign Flower, at Reading the 8th of this instant March 1684 who was tried and condemned at Reading ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2777A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34084</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13707220</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13707220</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101500</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63561)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1054:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A True narrative of the confession and execution of Ensign Flower, at Reading the 8th of this instant March 1684 who was tried and condemned at Reading ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Mallet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1684]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Executions and executioners --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101500:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
            <head>A TRUE NARRATIVE Of THE CONFESSION AND EXECUTION Of Enſign <hi>Flower,</hi> At READING the 8th of this Inſtant <hi>March</hi> 1684.</head>
            <head type="sub">Who was Tryed and condemned at <hi>Reading, February the 28th.</hi> for Killing of Capt. <hi>Powney</hi> at <hi>VVindſor.</hi> With a full Account of his penitent behaviour during the time of his Impriſonment.</head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>FLower,</hi> the unhappy Subject of this diſcourſe, was a Gentleman of a good Family, and one who wanted none of thoſe Ornaments which a civil and generous Education could accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh him with: he after ſome time apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf more particularly to Arms which he had always a natural inclination too; and ſo well improv'd himſelf in Martial Diſcipline that at length he received a Commiſſion from his preſent Majeſty to be Enſign in one of the Companys of the Foot Guards, in which Command he always behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101500:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->like a Gentleman, and a Soldier ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſince Mr. <hi>Powney Purvior</hi> to his ſacred Majeſty, and a Gentleman otherwiſe of a very conſiderable eſtate and quality bought a Commiſſion for a Captain in the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany where Mr. <hi>Flower</hi> was Enſign, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Windſor</hi> in company with Captain <hi>Pots</hi> Deputy Governour under his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> the preſent Conſtable of the Caſtle, <hi>&amp;</hi> Mr. <hi>Flower,</hi> he obſerved <hi>ſome</hi> little Annimoſities paſſed betwen Capt. <hi>Pots</hi> and Mr. <hi>Flower,</hi> which like a true Friend and good Chriſtian, he endeavoured to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, perſwading Mr. <hi>Flower</hi> to abate of that heat and paſſionate temper which he too much indulged, &amp; upon thoſe grounds <hi>which</hi> perhaps <hi>vvere</hi> falſe, however uncertain, and that 'tvvould better become him to ſeal a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect friendſhip and amity with that worthy perſon Capt. <hi>Pots</hi> than ſuffer his Blood to ferment into rage and diſorder, which might be the occaſion of future miſchiefs <hi>vvhich vvere</hi> ſooner <hi>committed</hi> than either repented of or redreſſed.</p>
            <p>This ſober advice from Capt. <hi>Powney</hi> made at preſent ſome impreſſion on Mr. <hi>Flower,</hi> conſidering the Captain both as his friend &amp; that duty and reſpect he ſtood more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly obliged to render him, as his Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Officer, ſo that during their ſtay together the Storm which before had too violently raged in his outward expreſſions ſeemed wholly allayed, at leaſt confined to his own
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101500:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->Breaſt. After ſometime they went out to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from the <hi>three Tun Tavern</hi> into the Street Capt. <hi>Pots</hi> and Mr. <hi>Flower</hi> being ſome paces before, on a ſudden Capt. <hi>Powney</hi> heard the claſhing of Swords, and making haſte after his <hi>company,</hi> ſaw Capt <hi>Pots</hi> and Mr. <hi>Flower</hi> engaged with their Swords <hi>dravvn and</hi> vigorouſly <hi>paſſing</hi> at one another, when coming <hi>up</hi> to them he <hi>called</hi> to Mr. <hi>Flower</hi> and deſired him to put up his Sword, which he taking no Notice of, Capt <hi>Powney,</hi> told him he <hi>muſt</hi> not ſee Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>committed</hi> in his <hi>company &amp;</hi> by thoſe he <hi>eſteemed</hi> his friends that he was his captain and <hi>commanded him</hi> to deſiſt. Upon which 'tis ſaid Mr. <hi>Flower</hi> replyed, be who you will, if you <hi>come</hi> within the reach of <hi>my</hi> Sword I will run <hi>you</hi> thorow: the Captain <hi>more</hi> friendly than cautiouſly throwing <hi>himſelf</hi> in betvveen <hi>them with</hi> a deſign to part <hi>them; Flower</hi> ran <hi>him</hi> through the Body, vvhich proving <hi>mortal</hi> he ſoon after died of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Flower</hi> had <hi>wounded</hi> Cap. <hi>Pots</hi> in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places, but upon the fall of Cap. <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> the people came in and apprehended Mr: <hi>Flower,</hi> who <hi>was committed</hi> to <hi>Reading Goal,</hi> and on <hi>February</hi> the 28th at the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes there held, arraigned and condemned.</p>
            <p>Great interceſſion was made by Mr. <hi>Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er's</hi> Mother to obtain his Pardon, vvith ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great offers for ſaving his Life, or at leaſt <hi>changing his Sentence</hi> of Death into Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101500:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->but all endeavours proved <hi>unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful,</hi> he having <hi>formerly,</hi> as 'tis ſaid, <hi>taſted</hi> of his <hi>Majestys gracious favour, and</hi> the vvhole Action <hi>appearing</hi> at his Tryal ſo <hi>much</hi> to his <hi>diſadvantage</hi> he was this, Day Executed at <hi>Auckland End</hi> near <hi>Reading.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During his Impriſonment he behaved himſelf with all the marks of Penitence and Contrition, which gained him the favour of ſome few days reſpit, that he might the better prepare himſelf for his latter end which was ſo faſt approaching. But the great God, who is often pleaſed to ſanctifie our greateſt afflictions to us, and by his infinite mercy ſweeten that cup of ſorrow which by our own ſins we have daſhed with Gall, was pleaſed to give this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant Criminal a true ſight of all his miſdeeds, and by the power of his Gracious Spirit an utter abhorrence of thoſe Evil ways, which the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil too often inſnare us with.</p>
            <p>On the eighth of this Inſtant, atten in the Morning, he was conducted by the Sheriff to <hi>Auckland End</hi> the place of his Execution, where after the ſinging of a pſalm he went to his Devotion, and takeing ſolemn leave of his Friends, after ſome ſhort Ejaculatory prayers the ſentence of Death was executed upon him.</p>
            <trailer type="license">Entered according to <hi>ORDER.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by</hi> E. Mallet, <hi>in</hi> Black-Horſe-Alley <hi>near</hi> Fleet-Bridge.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
